A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Secretary of Commonwealth, 2004-2017
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Virginia Secretary of Commonwealth, 2004-2017
The Library of Virginia
52237
1.3 cu.ft. (4 boxes)
Virginia. Office of the Secretary of Commonwealth
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred on 22 January 2018 by the Office of the Secretary of the Commonwealth, 1111 East Broad Street, 4th Floor, Richmond, Virginia, 23219.
Historical Information
The Office of the Secretary of the Commonwealth has evolved from early colonial times when there existed a Secretary of the Colony. Thomas Nelson held the position of the first Secretary of Virginia in 1776. Early Secretaries were elected by the public. An Act of the General Assembly in 1920 changed the election to a joint vote of the General Assembly. In a 1930 Act the duties of the Secretary were redefined with the Secretary of the Commonwealth serving as the ex officio secretary of the Governor, as custodian of many official State records, and as keeper of the Greater and Lesser Seals of the Commonwealth. The office of the Secretary has gradually acquired other functions, such as: service of out-of-state civil process; appointment and regulation of notaries public; and registration and oversight of lobbyists. The Office became a gubernatorial appointment subsequent to a 1958 Act of the Assembly. The Secretary of the Commonwealth is under the jurisdiction of the Governor's Office. The Secretary is appointed by the Governor for a term of four years. Currently the Secretary of the Commonwealth is responsible for gubernatorial appointments, clemency and restoration of civil rights requests and extraditions. Additional activities include: serving as ex officio Secretary to the Governor; serving as keeper of the seals of the Commonwealth; compiling and publishing the annual Blue Book; commissioning and regulating notary publics, including the publication of a Notary Handbook and conduct of disciplinary hearings; promulgating the lobbying disclosure requirements, registration of lobbyists, and recording of lobbying reports; servicing the civil process of out-of-state defendants and other parties; and authenticating and certifying the records of the courts and of any state agency.
Scope and Content
The records, 2004-2017, of the Secretary of the Commonwealth are arranged alphabetically by folder title and housed in four boxes. Included are executive directives and orders, joint declarations, judicial oaths and special appointments, orders, proclamations, writs, and other sundry materials. The majority of the records are from the administration of Governor Terry McAuliffe (2014-2018), but also include the administrations of Governor Mark Warner (2002-2006), Governor Timothy Kaine (2006-2010), and Governor Robert McDonnell (2010-2014).
The Executive Orders Digital Collection includes executive orders and executive directives issued by Governors Warner, Kaine, McDonnell, and McAuliffe.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
Contents List
- Boundary changes, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
- Compacts, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Compacts, 2015 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Compacts, 2016 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Constitutional Amendment to Section 6-A of Article X, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Executive Directives (No. 1-13), 2014-2017 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Executive Orders (No. 1-14), 2014 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Executive Orders (No. 15-37), 2014 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Executive Orders (No. 38-50), 2015 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Executive Orders (No. 51-60), 2016 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Executive Orders (No. 61-76), 2017 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Joint declaration, 2014 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Judges, Substitute, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Judges, Substitute, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Judges, Substitute, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Judges, Substitute, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Judges, Substitute, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Judges, Substitute, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Judicial commissions, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Judicial commissions, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Judicial commissions, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Judicial commissions, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Judicial commissions, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Judicial commissions, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Judicial commissions, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Judicial commissions, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Judicial commissions, 2013 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Judicial oaths, 2013 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Judicial oaths, 2014 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Judicial oaths, 2015 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Judicial oaths, 2016 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Judicial oaths, 2017 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Order for Restoration of Rights, 2016 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Proclamations, 2014-2015 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Writs of Special Elections, 2014-2016 (Box 4, Folder 5)